Guide to the Samuel Moss Carter Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Samuel Moss Carter Papers
1923-1995
RG 268
Yale University Divinity School Library
14.5
(36 boxes)
Sermons, writings, notes, teaching materials, and personal items provide substantive documentation of the life and work of Dr. Samuel Moss Carter, an early African American graduate of the Yale Divinity School, who was a Baptist pastor and professor of Church History, primarily in Virginia.
Carter, Samuel Moss, 1904-1999
Arrangement
I. Sermons / Addresses
II. Course-Related Materials
III. Notes
IV. Writings
V. Related to Organizations / Institutions
VI. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Moss Carter was born October 20, 1904, in New Haven, Pennsylvania and grew up in Columbus, Ohio. He was a third generation Baptist minister; his father, Rev. John Wesley Carter later served for a time at the prominent Providence Baptist Church in Chicago, Illinois.
After receiving a B.A. from Ohio State University in 1927, Carter went on to study at the Yale Divinity School, one of few students of color at the time. He graduated with a B.D. in 1930 and continued graduate study toward a Ph.D. at Yale but did not complete the degree.
Following his time at Yale Divinity School, Carter served as Assistant Professor of Philosophy and Religion at Shaw University in North Carolina and served as a pastor in Baptist churches, including in Winston, North Carolina. In 1944 he became the pastor of First Institutional Baptist Church in St. Petersburg, Florida. In 1948 he left Florida to work at Virginia Union University in Richmond, Virginia, serving as Dean for three years and as Professor of Church History and Missions at Virginia Union University and the Union Theological Seminary in Richmond until 1979. In 1950, Carter became pastor of First Baptist Church, Centralia, Virginia, where he served for forty years before retiring in 1990.
Carter received a Master in Theology in 1957 and a D.D. from Union Theological Seminary in 1982. He died on May 5, 1999.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Symone B. Scales, 2015-2016
Scope and Contents
Sermons, writings and notes, teaching materials, and personal items provide substantive documentation of the work of Dr. Samuel Moss Carter, an early African American graduate of the Yale Divinity School.
As noted in a letter from Carter's daughter, the donor of the collection, "Dr. Carter's collected works provide a unique and intimate portrait of a dedicated Baptist minister and theologian and reflect the tenor of the country from the late 1930s through the 1970s, and in particular the influence that the Yale experience undoubtedly had on his ministry."
Combining pastoral work with academic work throughout his career, Carter had a particular interest in documenting Black Christianity in the United States. His 1957 Master's thesis was titled "Representative Negro Baptist Preachers" and the dissertation he prepared for a Yale Ph.D degree (not completed) was "The Religion of the American Negro Slave."
The many sermons by Carter and his writings and notes on Black preaching in this collection provide unique insight on the Black church in the mid-20th century. In an interview for a newspaper article published in Richmond News Leader at the time of his retirement as pastor of First Baptist Church of Centralia, Carter indicated that he had noticed four kinds of Black preachers over the years: "The first kind is the kind like up north, who follow the white method. They just stand up there and talk nice. Another is the ones who sing the Gospel, who have what you call 'The Tone.' Then there's the 'emphasis' kind, the kind identified with Virginia. They just know how to emphasize different words, and to just use a lovely emphasis. The last kind is the kind that combines all of that."
Carter was a meticulous keeper of records, saving notes, papers, syllabi, and writings from throughout his long life. In most cases, materials in the collection have been kept together according to the labels on folders that Carter created, though the folders may have contained a fairly wide spectrum of types of material.
Series I, Sermons / Addresses, is divided according to different systems that Carter had in place to file his sermons, including by theme, by a numbered sequence, and by date. Series II, Course-Related Materials, is divided into two sections, "Courses taken" and "Courses taught." While every effort has been made to distinguish between the two types of material, not all documents were well-marked. The Notes of Series III have been organized alphabetically by topic. Again in this series, the lines between topics may be quite blurry, but a sense of Carter's interests shows through clearly. The notes include both handwritten notes and collected articles or newsclippings. The writings of Series IV include a few published items as well as essays written while at Yale Divinity School and other unpublished essays. Series V contains primarily documentation of institutions and organizations that Carter served. Series VI, Personal Items and Memorabilia, includes a small amount of correspondence as well as biographical documentation and photographs, including of his time at Yale Divinity School.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
African American clergy; African American preaching; Carter, Samuel Moss, 1904-1999
- Sermons / Addresses, Series I
  - By theme
    - All Saints Day (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Building (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Christmas (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Church (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Emancipation (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Fourth of July (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Funeral (1) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Funeral (2) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Funeral (3) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Funeral (4) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Minister Seminar (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Mother's Day (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Race (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Stewardship (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Youth (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Dated sequence
    - 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1984 (1) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1984 (2) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1986-1987 (1) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1986-1987 (2) (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1987 (1) (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1987 (2) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1988 (1) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1988 (2) (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1989 (1) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1989 (2) (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1989 (3) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Numbered sequence
    Scope and Contents
    The numbers in this section refer to Carter's notations on packets of sermons that included twenty to forty sermons each. There was not a discernable gathering principle for the packets, by date or theme.
    - 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 4 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 5 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 6 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 7 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 8 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 9 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 10 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 11 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 12 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 14 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 15 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 16 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 17 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 18 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 19 (1) (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 19 (2) (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 20 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 21 (1) (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 21 (2) (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 21 (3) (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 22 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 23 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 26 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 28 (1) (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 28 (2) (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 30 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 31 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 32 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 33 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 34 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 35 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 40 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 41 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 42 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - 43 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - 44 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - 46 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - 47 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - 48 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 49 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 50 (1) (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 50 (2) (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 53 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 54 (1) (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 54 (2) (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 57 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 60 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 61 (1) (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 61 (2) (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - 62 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - 63 (1) (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 63 (2) (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 64 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - 71 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - 72 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - 73 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - 74 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - 75 (1) (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 75 (2) (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 90 (1) (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - 90 (2) (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 91 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Radio addresses
    - Radio Addresses (1) (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Radio Addresses (2) (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Other sermons
    - Miscellaneous, including typed sermons: "Moving Mountains of Race Prejudice," "A New World A Comin'", "Goodwill for Retaliation", "The Conquest of Fear", No date (Box 14, Folder 1-7)
    - Miscellaneous, from packets labeled "Best sermons" and "Special Sermons", No date (Box 35, Folder 1-4)
    - Christmas sermons, No date (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Installation and anniversary sermons, No date (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Revival sermons, No date (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Sermons on the Church, No date (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Sermons on the Apostle Paul, No date (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous handwritten sermons, including "The Cross of Circumstance," "Do You Belong to God?", "The Unavoidable God", "Transfigured Living", No date (Box 36, Folder 2-3)
    - Sermon notes, sermons not preached, No date (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Sermons by others, No date (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous, including typed sermons "Life's Boundaries", "The Rich Fool" (Box 15, Folder 1-7)
- Course-Related Materials, Series II
  - Courses taken
    - Bible Survey, 1940-1941 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Church History, 1930-1931 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Christian Doctrine, 1940-1949 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Education (Secondary), 1936 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Educational Psychology (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Educational History, 1933 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Ethics (Professor Calhoun) (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Ethics (Professor Richard Niebuhr) (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Ethics (Professor Reinhold Niebuhr) (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Ethnography (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Old Testament Exegesis, 1942 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Old Testament History and Literature, 1940 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Old Testament History, 1953-1954 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Old Testament Prophets, 1937,1940 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Philosophy 201 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Philosophy 301 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Philosophy 302 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Philosophy 602 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Psychology 201, 1934 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Psychology 202, 1933 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Religion and Contemporary Politics (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Religion (Professor Calhoun) (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Spiritual Content of Literature (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Universal Education in the South (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Courses taught
    - Baptist History, Church Administration and Polity, 1961,1966 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Black Christian Leaders (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Black Church (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Black Preachers, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Black Religion, American, 1979 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Christianity, American, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Christian Missions, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Christianity in Modern Europe, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Christian Thought (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Church History (1 of 11), 1966, 1967,1968,1969,1970,1973,1977,1978 (Box 18, Folder 10)
      Course titles include Early Church History, Modern Church History, American Church History, European Church History, Modern and American Church History, History of Christian Thought
    - Church History (2 of 11) (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Church History (3 of 11) (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Church History (4 of 11) (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Church History (5 of 11) (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Church History (6 of 11) (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Church History (7 of 11) (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Church History (8 of 11) (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Church History (9 of 11) (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Church History (10 of 11) (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Church History (11 of 11) (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Church Ministry, 1973-1974 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Church Ministry, 1974-1975 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Historical and Theological Studies, 1979 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Psychology of Religion (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Religious Cults and Sects (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Rural Church (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Notes, Series III
  Many of the notes in this section are handwritten notes taken by Carter from his reading or in class. Some categories also contain collected articles and newsclippings on the subject.
  - Baptists (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Bible (1 of 3) (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Bible (2 of 3) (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Bible (3 of 3) (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Black Church (1 of 2) (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Black Church (2 of 2) (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Black Preachers (1 of 2) (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Black Preachers (2 of 2) (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Christianity (1 of 2) (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Christianity (2 of 2) (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Christian Missions (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Christian Ministry (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Church History (1 of 20) (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Church History (2 of 20) (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Church History (3 of 20) (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Church History (4 of 20) (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Church History (5 of 20) (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Church History (6 of 20) (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Church History (7 of 20) (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Church History (8 of 20) (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Church History (9 of 20) (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Church History (10 of 20) (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Church History (11 of 20) (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Church History (12 of 20) (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Church History (13 of 20) (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Church History (14 of 20) (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Church History (15 of 20) (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Church History (16 of 20) (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Church History (17 of 20) (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Church History (18 of 20) (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Church History (19 of 20) (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Church History (20 of 20) (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Education (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Educational Psychology (1 of 3) (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Educational Psychology (2 of 3) (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Educational Psychology (3 of 3) (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Ethics (1 of 3) (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Ethics (2 of 3) (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Ethics (3 of 3) (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - German (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Human Geography (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Negro Church (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Old Testament (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Philosophy of Religion (1 of 3) (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Philosophy of Religion (2 of 3) (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Philosophy of Religion (3 of 3) (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Practical Theology (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Psychology of Religion (1 of 3) (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Psychology of Religion (2 of 3) (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Psychology of Religion (3 of 3) (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Religion of American Negro Slave (1 of 5) (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Religion of American Negro Slave (2 of 5) (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Religion of American Negro Slave (3 of 5) (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Religion of American Negro Slave (4 of 5) (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Religion of American Negro Slave (5 of 5) (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Religious Education (1 of 3) (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Religious Education (2 of 3) (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Religious Education (3 of 3) (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Religious Cults (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Systematic Theology (1 of 2) (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Systematic Theology (2 of 2) (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Misc. Notes (1 of 7) (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Misc. Notes (2 of 7) (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Notes (3 of 7) (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Misc. Notes (4 of 7) (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Notes (5 of 7) (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Misc. Notes (6 of 7) (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Misc. Notes (7 of 7) (Box 29, Folder 7)
- Writings, Series IV
  - Article: "What It Means To Follow Christ" - published in The Baptist Herald, No date (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Essays: regarding the Ashanti (African people), No date (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Essays: regarding religion in West Africa, No date (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Essays: written at Yale Divinity School, including regarding history of Christian doctrine, Christian theology, Social ethics, circa 1928-1930 (Box 30, Folder 3-6)
  - Essays: written at Yale Divinity School, including regarding Christian theology, the Trinity, "The Religious Thought of Douglas Clyde Macintosh", circa 1928-1930 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Essays: including regarding religion of American Negro slave, Morality and Religion, Ethics and Eschatology in the Teachings of Jesus, No date (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Essays: including "The Conversion of a Skeptic", Religious Epistemology, "Religion and Ethics", No date (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Lectures on Paul, No date (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - Master's thesis: "Representative Negro Baptist Preachers", 1957 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - "The Religion of the American Negro Slave" (dissertation prepared for Yale Ph.D. - degree not completed), 1940 (Box 31, Folder 2)
- Related to Organizations / Institutions, Series V
  - Regarding plans for church buildings, 1955, 1976 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - First Baptist Institutional Church, St. Petersburg, Florida, 1946-1956 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - First Baptist Church, Centralia and Richmond, Virginia, 1950-1989 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Bethany Baptist Church, Columbus, Ohio, 1964, 1971 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Bethel Baptist Church, Jacksonville, Florida, 1923, 1927 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Second Baptist Church, Columbus, Ohio, 1961 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Shiloh Baptist Church, Washington, D.C., 1976-1977 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - First Baptist Church, Chillicothe, Ohio, 1954-1974 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Tabernacle Baptist Church, Augusta, Georgia, 1930, 1957 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Union University, Summer Seminar, 1965-1970 (Box 32, Folder 10-11)
  - Virginia Union University, including regarding chapel services, retreat, Ministerial Fellowship, 1967-1977 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Union University - workshop on preaching, memorial service for John Malcus Ellison, 1976, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 2)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series VI
  - Biographical Information, 1963- (Box 33, Folder 3)
    Including regarding 50th wedding anniversary (Nellie S. Carter, wife), daughter Symone Carter, honorary degree from Virginia Union University, retirement from First Baptist Church, Richmond, article in Richmond News Leader
  - Journal / writing book / personal notes, no date (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - King James Version Bible, personal copy (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Pastoral records - weddings and funerals (3 bound volumes), 1949-1990 (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, including letters in search of teaching positions and to Yale Divinity School professors, 1932-1945 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, primarily related to Baptist Church and Virginia Union University, 1952-1995 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, primarily from Carter's years at Yale Divinity School, including portraits of YDS professors, Carter with fellow students, circa 1928-1930 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, including from 90th birthday and with deacons of First Baptist Church, Richmond, 1992-1994 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Greeting cards received from family and friends (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Favorite hymns (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Prayers and Invocations (Box 34, Folder 5-6)
  - Diplomas, 1923-1981 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    North High School, Columbus, Ohio (1923); Ohio State University (B.A., 1927); Yale Divinity School (B.D., 1930); Union Theological Seminary in Virginia (Master of Theology, 1957); Virginia Union University (D.D., 1981)